#广西·桂林
Guilin, Guangxi
#在桂林 到处都是风景
In Guilin, there are beautiful scenes everywhere
#但是 到中午了 也该吃饭了
Now it's noon. Time for lunch!
#前面有一个步行街
There's a pedestrian shopping street ahead
#我们看一看那边有什么好吃的
Let's take a look and find some delicious food there
#糯米饭：3-6元  大叔 我问一下这个
(Glutinous rice ball: 3-6 yuan)
Uncle, may I ask
#三到六块钱 有什么区别
What's the difference between a 3-yuan rice ball and a 6-yuan rice ball?
#不就放多一点吗
Just more rice
#饭放多一点
More rice?
#饭放多一点 也可以加根香肠
More rice, or an extra sausage   #有一句字幕没有打上去，上传的时候加上：买两个糯米饭尝尝 (Let's buy two rice balls and have a try!)
#我要一个4块的 加绿豆蓉的
I'd like a 4-yuan rice ball with mung bean paste
#要不要辣椒 要辣椒
-Do you want chili?
-Yes please
#可以加辣椒
We can add chili in the rice ball
#这个就是咱们要的4块钱的糯米饭
This is our 4-yuan glutinous rice ball
#糯米饭是从3块钱到6块钱不等
The rice balls vary from 3 yuan to 6 yuan
#可能里面会加不同的料
With different ingredients inside
#咱们是3块钱的糯米饭
For this one, 3 yuan for the rice ball
#加了1块钱的绿豆蓉
With 1-yuan mung bean paste
#你像糯米饭是软软糯糯的 对不对
Generally glutinous rice is soft and sticky, right?
#咱们一摸起来就是 很软
You can feel the softness as soon as you touch it
#但是这个东西 刚才我摸的时候
But this one... when I touched it just now
#它会有点硬
It was somewhat hard
#我没想到 竟然是 妙脆角
I didn't expect it was Bugles actually
#糯米饭 其实和我的拳头差不多大
This rice ball is actually as big as my fist
#外面是 油亮油亮的
The outside looks oily and shiny
#以前吃的 大多数都是甜的
In the past, most of the glutinous rice that I had was sweet
#这次咱们尝试一下 辣的
This time let's try a spicy one
#刚才可能是因为我吃到绿豆蓉
Perhaps it was because I bit the mung bean paste just now
#真的是很奇妙
It tasted surprising
#这个糯米饭整体是 咸辣香的口感
The overall tastes are salty and spicy
#糯米吃起来是比较筋道 弹牙
The glutinous rice is relatively chewy     #还是al dente?
#但是绿豆蓉是比较细腻的
But the mung bean paste is delicate
#带有微微的的甜味
with slight sweetness
#和咸味并不是很冲突
It doesn't conflict much with the salty taste
#因为糯米饭当中加了一些香肠
Since there is some sausage in the rice
#而且香肠还有一些油放进去
the sausage comes with oil
#所以糯米饭吃起来一点都不会干
The rice ball is not dry at all
#不过有一个问题就是
But there is a problem
#吃第一口的时候会觉得很香 很辣
When you take the first bite, you'll feel it delicious and spicy
#但是吃多了 还是会觉得有点油腻的
But if you eat too much, you'll feel it's greasy
#这个量当主食吃 当一顿饭吃
The rice ball may not
#可能量不太够
be enough for a meal
#站在江边 当个小零食吃 就差不多
But it's Ok to have one as a snack as you stand by the riverside
#从最开始到现在 一直都是我在做
I've been cooking this from the very beginning till now
#开始 刚做 我还没会做
In the beginning, I didn't know how to cook it
#糯米 蒸也蒸不熟
I couldn't even steam the glutinous rice properly
#蒸不熟 不会蒸
The rice was not steamed well because I couldn't do it
#不懂什么叫蒸熟
I didn't know to what extent it was steamed well
#做了多久的糯米饭
How long had you been trying
#才开始能够蒸熟糯米饭
before you could steam it well?
#反正自己慢慢地摸索
Anyway, I slowly explored it
#什么叫熟
and understood what is "steamed well"
#这些调料 比如说香肠末还有牛肉丸子
These ingredients.. Such as sausage dices and beef ball
#都是自己想的 应该放什么吗
Did you come up with what to put in the rice ball by yourself?
#反正我是乱搞的
Actually I tried randomly
#一时一个名堂
I change them from time to time
#反正搞了 人家说好吃就可以了
As long as my customers like it
#我也不管它是什么样 难不难看 我不管
I don't really care how it looks, or if it's ugly
#你只要说 好吃
As long as you say "it's delicious!"
#就可以
That's fine
#阿姨 我问一个问题就是
Auntie, may I ask a question
#咱们这边吃糯米饭 都是加辣椒的吗
Do local people always eat glutinous rice with chili?
#大多数都放辣椒 都是放辣椒
-Most of them do
-Most people eat glutinous rice with chili?
#基本上都放 少数不要
Most people do. A few of them don't.
#其实这个糯米饭 是有点咸辣味道
Actually this glutinous rice is somewhat salty and spicy
#一点点微辣吧 对
-A little spicy. -Yeah.
#对于你们来说是微辣
It might be slightly spicy for you
#但对于外地人来说 可能就是有点辣了
But for people from other places, it might be spicy enough
#小孩都可以吃
Even kids here can eat this
#微辣
It's just a little bit spicy
#肯定外地人不吃辣椒的 他就怕辣
Of course, it's spicy for those who are afraid of spicy food
#吃辣椒的 他就不觉得辣
But not spicy for spicy food lovers
#好瘦啊 真的能把这个东西抬起来吗
You are so thin... Can you really lift this?
#现在抬不动了
Can't do it now
#刚才走的时候 我说
When I left there, I said
#阿姨这个饭比你还要重
Auntie, the rice is even heavier than yourself
#阿姨说 原来还能抬得动糯米饭
The auntie said that she could lift it by herself in the past
#现在已经抬不动了
But not anymore
#一方面是她太瘦 另一方面是这饭太重
On the one hand, she is too thin. On the other hand, the rice is too heavy
#这样脸好像更肥嘟嘟一些
My cheeks look chubby in this way
#我刚才在景区还帮一个大叔拍了照
I just took a photo for an uncle at the scenic spot
#他很开心 拍的不错
He was very happy. I did a good job!
#关 注
#雪 鱼 探 店
Subscribe to "Xue yu tan dian"